{"tossups": [{"question": "One figure with this surname introduced an unpopular \u201cQuota System\u201d of drafting sailors into the Royal Navy, while another established a reputation for honesty as Paymaster of the Forces during the \u201cBroad Bottom\u201d ministry. That figure with this surname teamed up with the Duke of Newcastle to form a ministry which saw the capture of Guadeloupe and victories at the battle of Quiberon Bay and Lagos during an \u201cAnnus Mirabilis\u201d. A prime minister with this surname introduced Britain\u2019s first modern income tax and resigned over the issue of (*) Catholic Emancipation. The ministry of that Prime Minister saw the United Irishmen Revolt, the British invasion of Haiti, and the French Revolution. For 10 points, which surname was shared by the political leader of Britain during the Seven Years\u2019 War and the Whig Prime Minister of Britain from 1783 to 1801?\u00a0", "answer": "Pitt (accept William Pitt the Elder or William Pitt the Younger; accept the 1st Earl of Chatham)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pitt</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pitt"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept William Pitt the Elder or William Pitt the Younger; accept the 1st Earl of Chatham"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s construction of the fortifications of Derbent was later attributed to Alexander the Great by some Arabic sources. The scholar Borzuya first translated the Panchatantra into Pahlavi during this man\u2019s reign. This ruler supposedly created a \u201chuman garden\u201d after burying followers of Mazdak with their feet in the air. It didn\u2019t become a center of learning, but a city founded by this ruler was built as an exact replica, even down to the mulberry tree outside of a resident\u2019s house, of a different conquered city that he called (*) \u201cBetter than\u201d that conquered city. This ruler created four military districts for his domain, each defended by an army led by a sp\u0101hbed. This ruler was the first to take the Byzantine garrison town of Dara. After only eight years, this ruler broke an \u201cEternal Peace\u201d with Justinian. For 10 points, identify this Sassanid ruler of the middle 6th century CE.", "answer": "Khosrau I (accept Khosrau the Just or Anushirav\u0101n the Just; accept Chosroes, Khosrow, Khusrau, or Kisr\u0101 in place of \u201cKhosrau\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Khosrau I</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Khosrau I"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Khosrau the Just or Anushirav\u0101n the Just; accept Chosroes, Khosrow, Khusrau, or Kisr\u0101 in place of \u201cKhosrau\u201d"}, {"question": "Two answers required A commander from one of these powers complained of the other, \"Are your seamen to fill your casks with wine rather than powder?\" when that side couldn\u2019t supply enough gunpowder during a joint siege. The first official diplomatic contact between these two powers was established by John Frangipani. Gabriel de Luetz was an ambassador from one of these two powers who advised the other in its siege of Van. To [emphasize] counteract the alliance between these two powers, two embassies to (*) Rudolf II were led by the Sherley brothers. The imprisonment of a monarch of one of these powers after the Battle of Pavia was a factor in the invasion of Hungary by the other, leading to the Battle of Moh\u00e1cs [MO-hahtch]. For 10 points, name these two powers who controversially allied under Suleiman the Magnificent and Francis I against the Habsburgs.", "answer": "Ottoman Empire and France (both parts required; prompt on partial answer)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ottoman Empire and France</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ottoman Empire and France"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "both parts required; prompt on partial answer"}, {"question": "Hosea Stout led the \u201cwhittling and whistling brigade\u201d, a security force in this city, which deterred crime by doing the two title actions near suspicious-looking strangers. A \u201cuniversity\u201d in this city was headed by John C. Bennett before he was stripped of his positions for adultery. A newspaper called [this city\u2019s] Expositor published only a single issue because it was shut down for criticizing this city\u2019s mayor. A military force named for this city was joined by 200 Paiute soldiers in its attack on the (*) Baker-Fancher party. Named after a Hebrew word meaning \u201cthey are beautiful\u201d, this city\u2019s most famous residents moved there after they were exiled by Missouri Executive Order 44. The residence of most of the Mormon community just before moving to Utah, for 10 points, name this city in western Illinois.", "answer": "Nauvoo\u00a0", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nauvoo</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nauvoo"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Archaeologist Hormuzd Rassam was among the hostages taken by a ruler of this country after his request for British aid was ignored. The Gideon Force aided native Arbegnoch forces to expel a foreign occupation of this country. A ruler of this country attempted to use a cannon named \u201cSebastopol\u201d in the defense of a fortress at Amba Mariam, but it was too large to drag up the hill to the fort. Members of the Bloomsbury Group (*) pranked the Royal Navy by pretending to be part of this country\u2019s royal family to tour the HMS Dreadnought. The organization AFROMET seeks the return of 468 artifacts stolen from this country by the British after the Battle of Magdala, including nine replicas of the Tablets of Law called tabots; the loss in that battle led Emperor Tewodros II to kill himself. For 10 points, name this country in East Africa, which received British aid in its resistance against Italian occupation.", "answer": "Ethiopian Empire (accept Abyssinia)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Ethiopian <b><u>Empire</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ethiopian Empire"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Abyssinia"}, {"question": "A royal monopoly over this good was briefly interrupted as fifteen captaincies were given to private donataries to settle the coast where it was acquired. A virtual monopoly over this good, which previously competed with a transitory system dominated by truchements, was obtained after the destruction of a colony populated by both Catholics and Huguenots called France Antarctique. The discovery of a large source of one kind of this good in 1500 began the shift of global commerce from the Indian Ocean to the Atlantic and gave Europe an alternative to the Asian (*) sappan- variety. The first tightly-controlled feitorias in the New World were set up to trade for this good. A variety of this good was exported to Europe after trading with the Tupinamba people, and unusually was used to produce a red dye used for textiles like velvet. For 10 points, identify this commodity which gave Brazil its name and was, along with fur, the chief good exported from the Canadian hinterland.", "answer": "wood (accept brazilwood)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>wood</u></b>", "acceptable": ["wood"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept brazilwood"}, {"question": "It\u2019s not Hawaii, but a large effort to consolidate landholdings in this kingdom was ironically called the Great Partition. Religious freedom in this kingdom was granted to immigrants and foreigners in 1781 and Jews in 1782, despite citizens being unable to publicly practice any form of Christianity other than the state church at the time; those restrictions emerged to curb the influence of radical Pietist groups like the Gray Robes. A ruler of this kingdom launched a successful coup in 1772 against his own parliament, effectively ending the power of the (*) Francophilic Hats and the Russophilic Caps. A tour around the Gulf of Bothnia by a resident of this kingdom helped him develop a system most famously laid out in Systema Naturae. For 10 points, identify this kingdom whose Royal Academy of Sciences was founded in part by Carl Linnaeus.", "answer": "Kingdom of Sweden (accept Konungariket Sverige)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kingdom of Sweden</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kingdom of Sweden"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Konungariket Sverige"}, {"question": "One text describes a region on this body of water as a paradise made lush by water divinely brought up out of the ground and where \u201cthe raven croaks not/ the lion does not kill\u201d. Failaka Island was an important trading hub at the northern end of this body of water. Strabo describes the residents of Gerrha, believed to be on or near this body of water, as living in houses made of salt. Steffen Laursen has proposed that a system of symbols found in what is believed to be the (*) Dilmun culture on this body of water developed from trade with the Indus Valley. Foreign traders, such as from Meluhha and the aforementioned Dilmun, passing through this body of water before traveling upriver to his capital was a matter of pride for Sargon the Great. For 10 points, what is this body of water that the Tigris and Euphrates rivers flow into?", "answer": "Persian Gulf (prompt on \u201cIndian Ocean\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Persian Gulf</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Persian Gulf"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \u201cIndian Ocean\u201d"}, {"question": "George Holt published an \u201cUntold History\u201d of one variety of this foodstuff in 2014. A version of this foodstuff that originated in the early 1980s features ingredients like pork bone and lu\u00f3s\u012b [LOO-oh-sih] snail-based stock. The \u201cfried sauce\u201d variety of this foodstuff is served cold with vegetables such as sliced cucumbers and radishes, and another variety is made with kansui, or alkaline mineral water, and a production process for that variety was developed in 1958 by (*) Momofuku Ando. A popular variety of this foodstuff made with beef is named for this city of L\u00e1nzh\u014du [lahn-joh]. One variety of this foodstuff was introduced in the 1930s by the Prime Minister Phibun [pea-boon] to promote nationalism in his country, and that version of this foodstuff is served with scrambled egg, bean sprouts, and crushed peanuts. For 10 points, name this foodstuff whose varieties include Pad Thai and Ramen.\u00a0", "answer": "Noodles (accept Instant Noodles, Ramen, lu\u00f3s\u012b f\u011bn, zh\u00e1ji\u00e0ng mi\u00e0n, ni\u00far\u00f2u mi\u00e0n, or Pad Thai)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Noodles</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Noodles"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Instant Noodles, Ramen, lu\u00f3s\u012b f\u011bn, zh\u00e1ji\u00e0ng mi\u00e0n, ni\u00far\u00f2u mi\u00e0n, or Pad Thai"}, {"question": "In one story, a fictional ruler of this place joins a Muslim siege of Constantinople with gold-armored soldiers and 500 griffins. It\u2019s not in Africa or the Middle East, but this place was once thought to be bordered by a \u201cRed Sea\u201d. Mutineer Fort\u00fan Xim\u00e9nez (\u201cshe\u201d-\u201cMAIN\u201d-ayth) may have been the first to apply the modern name of this place to actual land. The writings of Francis Pretty provided the basis for a forgery perpetrated by the E Clampus Vitus fraternity regarding the history of this place. This place is ruled by Queen Calafia and inhabited by only women in the book (*) The Adventures of Esplandi\u00e1n. A map created by Eusebio Kino contributed to the end of the belief that this place was an island. The fame of the mineral wealth of this place led to it to be the first [emphasize] overseas area to be known in China as \u201cGold Mountain\u201d. For 10 points, identify this place, now two Mexican states and one American state home to Los Angeles.", "answer": "California (accept Baja California; antiprompt on New Albion)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>California</u></b>", "acceptable": ["California"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Baja California; antiprompt on New Albion"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable Weriyeng and fanur were two approaches to how this process was carried out. Earth ovens and stone flakes found on Enderby Island make it a confirmed boundary for the extent of this process. An early 20th century scholar depicted one stage of this process as an octopus, which occurred after an approximately 1,400 year \u201clong pause\u201d. The earliest phases of this process can be tracked through the distribution of the Lapita culture. In the 1970\u2019s, a resident of Satawal, (*) Mau Piailug, helped revive a set of skills used in this process, which were only believed to have been known by six people. The means by which this process occurred were tested through the voyages of the H\u014dk\u016ble\u02bba. For 10 points, name this process through which places like Rapa Nui and New Zealand came to be first inhabited.", "answer": "settlement of the Pacific (accept inhabitation, discovery, exploration, wayfinding, or similar words in place of \u201csettlement\u201d; accept Melanesia, Micronesia, or Polynesia in place of \u201cPacific\u201d; prompt on just \u201cexploration\u201d, \u201cnavigation\u201d, or \u201cwayfinding\u201d with \u201cOf where?\u201d; do not accept answers about non-Austronesian settlement of the region)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>settlement of the Pacific</u></b>", "acceptable": ["settlement of the Pacific"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept inhabitation, discovery, exploration, wayfinding, or similar words in place of \u201csettlement\u201d; accept Melanesia, Micronesia, or Polynesia in place of \u201cPacific\u201d; prompt on just \u201cexploration\u201d, \u201cnavigation\u201d, or \u201cwayfinding\u201d with \u201cOf where?\u201d; do not accept answers about non-Austronesian settlement of the region"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable\u00a0 Condottiero Filippo Strozzi led a French force that joined an unsuccessful attempt to prevent this political period. Margaret of Savoy, Duchess of Mantua was captured by the Forty Conspirators in their effort to end this political period. The shift in foreign policy caused by this political period allowed for the brief Dutch control of northeastern Brazil. The city of Ceuta was officially transferred as part of the treaty ending the war immediately following this political period. His defeat at the Battle of Alc\u00e2ntara ended (*) Ant\u00f3nio, Prior of Crato\u2019s attempt to prevent this political period. This political period resulted from the accession of the celibate Henry the Cardinal-King after the death at the Battle of Alc\u00e1cer Quibir of Sebastian I, the last king of the Aviz Dynasty. For 10 points, what was this political period lasting from 1580-1640 when a peninsula in southwestern Europe was ruled by a single monarch?", "answer": "Iberian Union (accept descriptive answers that suggest that Spain and Portugal are politically unified; prompt on \u201cPortuguese succession crisis\u201d or \u201cWar of Protuguese Succession\u201d with \u201cWhat was the result?\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Iberian Union</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Iberian Union"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept descriptive answers that suggest that Spain and Portugal are politically unified; prompt on \u201cPortuguese succession crisis\u201d or \u201cWar of Protuguese Succession\u201d with \u201cWhat was the result?\u201d"}, {"question": "A song supposedly composed by a man who fought the expansion of this empire was adapted and secretly passed down through the Chabad Rebbes until it was made public in 1958. Resistance fighters attempted to prevent the construction of a fort by this empire on the Sunzha River, but were mowed down as they tried to capture a cannon left in the open as bait. The fortified village, or aul [ah-OOL], of Gimry was a base for fighting against this empire during the Murid War. Most of the people living in the Kuban River basin were killed or deported by the forces of this empire seeking its pastureland. The Caucasian (*) Imamate formed to wage a holy war against this empire as it sought to join Georgia with the rest of its territory. The life of a warrior who fought both for and against this empire was fictionalized in the novella Hadji Murat. For 10 points, what is this empire whose holdings in the Caucasus were recreated by its successor, the Soviet Union?", "answer": "Russian Empire", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Russian Empire</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Russian Empire"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This leader lost one position after a vote of no confidence engineered by the monarchist Victor de Broglie. While Minister of the Interior, this leader helped put down a legitimist uprising by the Duchesse de Berry. This leader founded the liberal newspaper Le National, and as prime minister, he initiated a set of sloped walls whose boundaries still demarcate the city of Paris today. As a historian, this leader published a major history of the (*) French Revolution in 1827, which praised the Revolution of 1789 but criticized the Reign of Terror. Buildings like the Tuileries palace and the Hotel de Ville were burned after this first president of the French Third Republic ordered an assault led by Patrice McMahon. For 10 points, name this French leader who ordered the suppression of the Paris Commune during the \u201cBloody Week\u201d.", "answer": "Adolphe Thiers", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Adolphe <b><u>Thiers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Adolphe Thiers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A traveler from this modern country reported that after being granted guardianship of the Lighthouse of Alexandria, a foreigner had stolen its mirror and thrown it into the sea. A history written in this modern country describes the \u201cflying bridge\u201d built over the Euphrates at the Roman city of Zeugma. An unknown Roman in this modern country is believed to have first introduced the practice of changing \u201cflints into crystal by means of fire\u201d, otherwise known as glassblowing. An emissary from this modern country to Rome wrote of Roman sea (*) silk, despite never entering Roman territory, due to the machinations of Parthian officials. One man\u2019s return to this modern country after being captured at the Battle of Talas was recorded in the now mostly lost J\u012bngx\u00edngj\u00ec [cheeng-sheeng-jee]. For 10 points, what is this modern country, the home of such travelers as G\u0101n Y\u012bng and F\u01ce Xi\u01cen [shyen]?", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of China (accept Zh\u014dnggu\u00f3 or PRC)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>People\u2019s Republic of China</u></b>", "acceptable": ["People\u2019s Republic of China"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Zh\u014dnggu\u00f3 or PRC"}, {"question": "One organization criticized Stanley Gortikov, an executive in this industry, for only providing one blanket response in line with their goals instead of a series of specialized ones. An argument leveled against this industry was revealed to be a misinterpretation of a text about throat surgery undergone by Eddie Ojeda (oh-JAY-duh). A man working in this industry claimed that the political and media attention over one controversy was the result of \u201ca couple of blowjobs here and there\u201d. This industry was attacked for the alleged practice of (*) \u201cbackward masking\u201d. Three representatives of this industry defended it against an organization largely composed of politicians\u2019 wives in a 1985 Senate hearing over adult references in their work. Tipper Gore and the PMRC sought to regulate, for 10 points, what industry, which eventually adopted the Parental Advisory sticker to warn of explicit content?", "answer": "music industry (accept recording industry)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>music industry</u></b>", "acceptable": ["music industry"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept recording industry"}, {"question": "A Jethro Tull song named after this object repeats the line \u201cSo come all you lovers of the good life\u201d and begins by describing an \u201cOld woman with a barrow; life near ending.\u201d One character complains about another character named after this object for \u201changing oil lamps next to hardwood paneling\u201d and finding a jockstrap on the floor. The name of this object is a cheat in Age of Empires that turns Juggernaughts into amphibious units. Homer Simpson sues a restaurant whose name is a parody of this object for not giving him (*) \u201call he could eat\u201d as advertised. A character named after this object refuses to eat without his \u201cdining sock.\u201d After being found bound to a cannon on the seafloor, Bootstrap Bill serves under Davy Jones on this ship in the Pirates of the Caribbean series. For 10 points, name this ghost ship of European legend.", "answer": "Flying Dutchman", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Flying Dutchman</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Flying Dutchman"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "\u014cuy\u00e1ng X\u00fan\u2019s [shoon] calligraphy for one type of these objects was an important model for these objects in Vietnam until the 1940\u2019s. A predecessor to these objects was modeled after a triangle-like musical instrument. The state of Ch\u01d4 produced a type of these objects now known as \u201cant-nosed\u201d. Though their provenance is uncertain, a simplistic style of these objects has been attributed to the reign of D\u01d2ng Zhu\u00f3, who supposedly melted nine statues from the Q\u00edn Dynasty to make them. Many types of these objects were strung together in groups of 100 through the (*) holes in their centers. Ji\u0101oz\u01d0 [chyow-tsuh] emerged during the S\u00f2ng Dynasty and served a similar role to these objects. These objects took the place of bronze knife- and spade-shaped objects as media of exchange. For 10 points, identify these metallic objects that today come in denominations of yu\u00e1n.", "answer": "coins (prompt on \u201cmoney\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>coins</u></b>", "acceptable": ["coins"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \u201cmoney\u201d"}, {"question": "John Hunter is believed to have paid \u00a3500 for a \u201cgiant\u201d one of these objects from Ireland. Many people who worked with these objects in London operated out the Fortune of War public house. Robert Knox was caricatured as a black-furred monster for working with these objects. A group best known for working with these objects first did so to recoup back rent owed by a tenant named Donald. Metal devices called (*) mortsafes were used to protect these objects. A group who sold these objects were found out after attempting to sell to Guy\u2019s Hospital in London for medical training. Most famously traded in Edinburgh by Burke and Hare, for 10 points, identify these objects, which were illegally supplied through grave robbing or murder.", "answer": "dead bodies (accept synonyms like corpse or cadaver; prompt on \u201chumans\u201d or synonyms)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>dead bodies</u></b>", "acceptable": ["dead bodies"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept synonyms like corpse or cadaver; prompt on \u201chumans\u201d or synonyms"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s conquest of Chitradurga was delayed by a woman named Obavva, who killed most of a force infiltrating the city by beating them over the head with a large pestle as they exited a hole in the city wall single-file. On the death of a de jure ruler of his realm, this man supposedly watched the royal children playing, selecting the one who played with a jeweled dagger as the successor. This man fired one of his commanders for blinding the Sultan of the Maldives after conquering the islands. This man lost the battles of Porto Novo and Sholinghur to Sir (*) Eyre Coote, eventually leading to the Treaty of Mangalore with the British East India Company. This man\u2019s victory at the Battle of Pollilur included significant use of iron-tubed rockets. For 10 points, identify this de facto ruler of Mysore and father of Tipu Sultan.", "answer": "Hyder Ali", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hyder Ali</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hyder Ali"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}